[
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Compute the sum of the digits of 9997 \u00b7 7999",
        "ChoiceA": "22",
        "ChoiceB": "13",
        "ChoiceC": "31",
        "ChoiceD": "49",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "Other",
        "Explanation": "Note that 9997 = 10000 \u2212 3 and 7999 = 8000 \u2212 1, so the desired product is (10000 \u2212 3)(8000 \u2212 1) = 80000000 \u2212 10000 \u2212 24000 + 3 = 79966003, whose digits sum to 40",
        "Category": "Number Sense",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Compute the number of permutations of the digits {1, 2, 3, 4, 5} that have an odd units digit when read as a 5-digit number",
        "ChoiceA": "60",
        "ChoiceB": "72",
        "ChoiceC": "96",
        "ChoiceD": "48",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "72",
        "Explanation": "There are 3 choices for the units digit, and the remaining 4 digits can be permuted in 4! ways, so the total number of valid permutations is 4! \u00b7 3 = 72",
        "Category": "Combination",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": " Let a and b be real numbers such that a \u00b7 (a + b) = 2 and b \u00b7 (a + b) = 3. Compute a^2 + b^2",
        "ChoiceA": "12/5",
        "ChoiceB": "2",
        "ChoiceC": "13/5",
        "ChoiceD": "11/5",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "13/5",
        "Explanation": "Adding the given equations gives (a + b)(a + b) = 5, so a + b = \u00b1\u221a5. Without loss of generality, let a + b = \u221a5. Then, \u221a5a = 2, so a = 2/\u221a5 and b = 3/\u221a5, and a^2 + b^2 = 4/5 + 9/5 = 13/5. Note that taking a + b = \u2212\u221a5 would yield the same answer",
        "Category": "Algebra",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Theresa has 3 rods of equal length, which she can use to form an equilateral triangle with area A. She then cuts one of the rods in half and discards one of the halves. With her new set of rods, she can form a triangle with area c \u00b7 A for some real number c. Compute c^2",
        "ChoiceA": "1/4",
        "ChoiceB": "5/16",
        "ChoiceC": "1/16",
        "ChoiceD": "15/32",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "5/16",
        "Explanation": "Suppose that the three original rods each have length 4x. Then A = 4\u221a3x^2 by the formula for the area of an equilateral triangle. On the other hand, the area of an isosceles triangle with sides of length 4x, 4x, and 2x can be found by dropping an altitude to the side of length 2x. By the Pythagorean Theorem, the length of this altitude is x\u221a(4^2 \u2212 1^2) = x\u221a15, so the area of this triangle is (2x)(x\u221a15)/2 = \u221a15x^2. Thus, c^2 = (\u221a15/(4\u221a3))^2 = 5/16.",
        "Category": "Geometry",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Compute the smallest positive integer x for which 1 + 11 + 21 + 31 + \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 + (10x + 1) is divisible by 131",
        "ChoiceA": "130",
        "ChoiceB": "26",
        "ChoiceC": "131",
        "ChoiceD": "12",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "26",
        "Explanation": "Note that 1 + 11 + 21 + \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 + (10x + 1) = 10 \u00b7 (0 + 1 + \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 + x) + (x + 1) = 5x \u00b7 (x + 1) + (x + 1) = (5x+1)(x+1). Since 131 is prime, the smallest possible value of x is the smallest positive integer that satisfies 5x + 1 = 131, so x = 26.",
        "Category": "Number Sense",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Call an ordered pair of not necessarily distinct positive integers (a, b) a sibling pair if every digit in a is also in b and every digit in b is also in a. For example, (112, 122) is a sibling pair. Compute the number of ordered pairs of positive integers strictly less than 100 that are sibling pairs",
        "ChoiceA": "90",
        "ChoiceB": "189",
        "ChoiceC": "198",
        "ChoiceD": "153",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "189",
        "Explanation": "Note that if a = b, then a and b are inherently siblings, so there are 99 such pairs here. Otherwise, at least one of the numbers must have two digits. If exactly one of the numbers has two digits, then the only way a and b can be siblings is if the number with two digits is a multiple of 11 and the single-digit number is that number divided by 11. Accounting for order, this yields 2 \u00b7 9 = 18 pairs. Finally, if both of the numbers have two digits and are note equal, then a and b must be distinct permutations of each other. Because 0 cannot be a digit in either a or b in this case, there are 9 \u00b7 8 = 72 such pairs. The total number of sibling pairs with both numbers less than 100 is therefore 99 + 18 + 72 = 189",
        "Category": "Number Sense",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Compute the remainder when 2^100 \u2212 100 is divided by 2^99 \u2212 99",
        "ChoiceA": "98",
        "ChoiceB": "2^99 \u2212 198 ",
        "ChoiceC": "2^99 \u2212 2^98",
        "ChoiceD": "198",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "98",
        "Explanation": "Note that 2 \u00b7 (2^99 \u2212 99) = 2^100 \u2212 198, so the desired remainder is 2^100 \u2212 100 \u2212 (2^100 \u2212 198) = 98",
        "Category": "Number Sense",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Find the first nonzero digit to the right of the decimal point in the decimal expansion of the fraction 1/12345",
        "ChoiceA": "1",
        "ChoiceB": "4",
        "ChoiceC": "5",
        "ChoiceD": "8",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "8",
        "Explanation": "There will be 5 \u2212 1 = 4 leading zeros to the right of the decimal point in this decimal expansion, so it suffices to compute \u230a100000/12345\u230b, which is 8.",
        "Category": "Number Sense",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Chord AB is drawn in circle \u03b3 with center O. Point P lies on AB such that OP = 8, OB = 10, and PB = 10. Compute AP",
        "ChoiceA": "18/5",
        "ChoiceB": "16/5",
        "ChoiceC": "2",
        "ChoiceD": "9/5",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "18/5",
        "Explanation": "Let AP = x, and suppose that line OP intersects \u03b3 at points X and Y, with points X, O, P, and Y collinear in that order. Since OB = 10 is a radius of \u03b3, we know that XO = 10 and PY = 10 \u2212 8 = 2. Then by Power of a Point on point P, we have PX \u00b7 PY = PA \u00b7 PB, so (10 + 8) \u00b7 2 = 10x and x = 18/5",
        "Category": "Geometry",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Jimmy has an unfair six-sided die for which the probability that the die shows the face with the integer 1 \u2264 i \u2264 6 is proportional to i. His friend James has a different unfair six-sided die for which the probability that the face shown has the integer 1 \u2264 i \u2264 6 is proportional to 7 \u2212 i. They each roll their respective dice once and add together the two numbers that are shown. Compute the probability that this sum is even",
        "ChoiceA": "24/49",
        "ChoiceB": "16/49",
        "ChoiceC": "25/49",
        "ChoiceD": "12/49",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "24/49",
        "Explanation": "The sum of the two numbers rolled is even if and only if the numbers showing on the two dice have the same parity. The probability that John\u2019s number is even is (2+4+6) / (1+2+3+4+5+6) = 12/21 = 4/7, so the probability that his number is odd is 1 \u2212 4/7 = 3/7. On the other hand, the probability that James\u2019s number is even is (5+3+1) / (1+2+3+4+5+6) = 9/21 = 3/7, so the probability that his number is odd is 1 \u2212 3/7 = 4/7. Thus, the desired probability is 4/7 \u00b7 3/7 + 3/7 \u00b7 4/7 = 24/49.",
        "Category": "Combination",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "For any positive integer n, let f(n) be the largest odd positive integer that divides n, and let g(n) be the largest power of 2 that divides n. For example, f(5) = 5 and g(5) = 1. Compute the sum of all positive integers n \u2264 2024 for which f(n) + 1 = g(n)",
        "ChoiceA": "2070",
        "ChoiceB": "1426",
        "ChoiceC": "315",
        "ChoiceD": "1302",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "1302",
        "Explanation": "Each integer n can be expressed in the form 2^a \u00b7 b for integers a and b, with b odd. By definition, f(n) = b and g(n) = 2^a, so b = 2^a \u2212 1. Then n = 2^a(2^a \u2212 1) = 4^a \u2212 2^a, so the possible values of n are 4^1 \u2212 2^1, 4^2 \u2212 2^2, 4^3 \u2212 2^3, 4^4 \u2212 2^4, and 4^5 \u22122^5. These sum to (4^1 + 4^2 + 4^3 + 4^4 + 4^5) \u2212 (2^1 + 2^2 + 2^3 + 2^4 + 2^5) = 4(1\u22124^5)/(1\u22124) \u2212 62, or 1302.",
        "Category": "Number Sense",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "The pairwise sums of the digits of some three-digit positive integer are 7, 11, and s. Compute the sum of all possible values of s",
        "ChoiceA": "70",
        "ChoiceB": "54",
        "ChoiceC": "50",
        "ChoiceD": "72",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "54",
        "Explanation": "Suppose that the number\u2019s digits are a, b, and c. Without loss of generality, let a+b = 7, let b+c = 11, and let a + c = s. Note that at most one of a, b, and c can be 0; otherwise, it would be impossible to obtain multiple distinct nonzero pairwise digit sums. Then adding these three equations and dividing by 2 yields a + b + c = 9 + s/2. Subtracting each of the equations from this then gives a = s/2 \u2212 2, b = 9 \u2212 s/2, and c = s/2 + 2. Each of a, b, and c must be between 0 and 9, inclusive, so s must be between 4 and 14, inclusive. In addition, s must be even because a + b + c = 9 + s/2 is an integer. Therefore, the possible values for s are 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, and 14, which sum to 54.",
        "Category": "Algebra",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Triangle ABC has a right angle at B and side lengths AB = 3 and BC = 4. Let D be the foot of the altitude from B to AC, and let points E and F be in the same plane as \u25b3ABC such that CE < AE and BDEF is a square. Compute the area of the region inside BDEF but outside \u25b3ABC",
        "ChoiceA": "36/25",
        "ChoiceB": "72/25",
        "ChoiceC": "48/25",
        "ChoiceD": "27/8",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "Other",
        "Explanation": "The side length of BDEF is 3\u00b74/5 = 12/5, so BF = 12/5. Note that the desired region is a right triangle. Call this triangle R. Because the side lengths of a square are parallel, we know that \u2220FBC \u223c= \u2220BCA. Therefore, R is similar to \u25b3ABC with scale factor (12/5)/4 = 3/5. The area of \u25b3ABC is 1/2 \u00b7 3 \u00b7 4 = 6, so the area of R is 6 \u00b7 (3/5)^2 = 54/25.",
        "Category": "Geometry",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "For each digit 0 \u2264 d \u2264 9, let f(d) be the number of possible tens digits of n^2 for positive integers n with units digit d. Compute f(0) + f(1) + \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 + f(9)",
        "ChoiceA": "42",
        "ChoiceB": "50",
        "ChoiceC": "34",
        "ChoiceD": "37",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "42",
        "Explanation": "We claim that f(0) = f(5) = 1 and f(d) = 5 for all other values of d, which yields an answer of 2(1) + 8(5) = 42. Note that a positive integer n can be expressed 10a + d for nonnegative integers a and d. Then, n^2 = 100a + 20ad + d^2, and note that 100a + 20ad + d^2 \u2261 20ad + d^2 mod 100. By inspection, if d = 0, then the tens digit is 0, and if d = 5, then the tens digit is 2. Now, consider the other possible values of d. Notice that these values of d are such that 20ad is equivalent to one of 0, 20a, 40a, 60a, or 80a modulo 100. Because the d^2 term adds a constant to these four values, the tens digit of n^2 will cycle within (0, 2, 4, 6, 8) or (1, 3, 5, 7, 9), in some order, so f(d) = 5 for these values of d, as claimed.",
        "Category": "Combination",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Brian is climbing a flight of 10 stairs by taking steps with alternating feet. He can climb 1 or 2 stairs in each step. Given that he must take his first and last steps with the same foot, compute the number of ways in which Brian can climb the stairs",
        "ChoiceA": "45",
        "ChoiceB": "44",
        "ChoiceC": "36",
        "ChoiceD": "35",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "45",
        "Explanation": "Note that the total number of steps that Brian takes must be odd. He must take at least 10/2 = 5 steps and at most 10/1 = 10, so he must take 5, 7, or 9 steps. The numbers of steps of 2 stairs that he takes in each of these cases is 5, 3, and 1, respectively, so the number of ways in which Brian can climb the stairs is (5 5) + (7 3) + (9 1) = 45.",
        "Category": "Combination",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Let N be the largest five-digit multiple of 99 whose digits are all distinct. Compute the units digit of N",
        "ChoiceA": "0",
        "ChoiceB": "9",
        "ChoiceC": "5",
        "ChoiceD": "3",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "3",
        "Explanation": "Since there is a multiple of 99 in every set of 100 consecutive integers, the largest possible such number must be between 98700 and 98799, inclusive. Note that 98700 \u2261 (987 \u00b7 1) mod 99, so 98700 \u2261 96 mod 99, and one possible value for N is 98700 + 3 = 98703. Note that no greater five-digit integer with distinct digits can be divisible by 99, so N = 98703, and it has units digit 3",
        "Category": "Number Sense",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": " Let d1 < d2 < \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 < dn be the n positive integer divisors of 126. Compute the remainder when d1^127 + d2^127 + \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 + dn^127 is divided by 127",
        "ChoiceA": "1",
        "ChoiceB": "41",
        "ChoiceC": "0",
        "ChoiceD": "12",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "Other",
        "Explanation": "Note that 127 is prime, so by Fermat\u2019s Little Theorem, we have that that di^127 \u2261 di mod 127. Then d1^127 + d2^127 + \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 + dn^127 \u2261 d1 + d2 + \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 + dn mod 127. Since 126 = 2 \u00b7 3^2 \u00b7 7, the sum of its positive integer divisors is (1 + 2)(1 + 3 + 3^2)(1 + 7) = 312, which is equivalent to 58 mod 127.",
        "Category": "Algebra",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Let ABCDEF be a hexagon with m\u2220ABC = m\u2220BCD = m\u2220CDE = m\u2220DEF = 120, AB = DE = 18, BC = CD = 15, and EF = 20. Compute AF^2",
        "ChoiceA": "170",
        "ChoiceB": "150",
        "ChoiceC": "175",
        "ChoiceD": "165",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "175",
        "Explanation": "First, observe that AB \u2225 DE. Let P and Q be the feet of the perpendiculars from C to lines AB and DE, respectively. Since m\u2220PBC = 180 \u2212 120 = 60, we know that triangles PBC and CDQ are 30-60-90 triangles. Then PQ = 15\u221a3 because CP = CQ = 15\u221a3/2. Now let R and S be the feet of the perpendiculars from F to lines AB and DE, respectively, so that \u25b3FES is also a 30-60-90 triangle. Then FS = 10\u221a3, so FR = 15\u221a3 \u2212 10\u221a3 = 5\u221a3. Finally, note that RA = ES = 10, so FA^2 = 10^2 + (5\u221a3)^2 = 175.",
        "Category": "Geometry",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Let S = 1 + 2i + 3i^2 + \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 + 2024i^2023, and let T = 2024 + 2023i + 2022i^2 + \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 + i^2023. Then there exist integers a and b such that S^2 + T^2 = a + bi. Compute the remainder when a + b is divided by 1000",
        "ChoiceA": "552",
        "ChoiceB": "105",
        "ChoiceC": "529",
        "ChoiceD": "104",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "Other",
        "Explanation": "Recall that the integer powers of i have values of 1, i, -1, and \u2212i for powers congruent to 0, 1, 2, and 3 mod 4, respectively. Then S = (1 \u2212 3 + 5 \u2212 7 + \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 \u2212 2023) + (2 \u2212 4 + 6 \u2212 \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 \u2212 2024) \u00b7 i, which has value \u22121012 \u2212 1012i. Note that S + T = 2025 \u00b7 (1 + i + i^2 + \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 + i^2023) = 0, so T = 1012 + 1012i. Finally, S^2 + T^2 = (\u22121012 \u2212 1012i)2 + (1012 + 1012i)^2 = 2 \u00b7 (1012 + 1012i)^2, which evaluates to 2 \u00b7 (1012^2 + 2 \u00b7 1012^2 \u00b7 i \u2212 1012^2) = 4 \u00b7 1012^2 \u00b7 i. Thus, a + b = 0 + 4 \u00b7 1012^2, which is equivalent to 4 \u00b7 12^2 = 576 mod 1000",
        "Category": "Algebra",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Compute the units digit of 1^1! + 2^2! + 3^3! + 4^4! + \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 + 2023^2023!",
        "ChoiceA": "3",
        "ChoiceB": "0",
        "ChoiceC": "4",
        "ChoiceD": "6",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "0",
        "Explanation": "Note that for every positive integer n \u2265 4, n! is divisible by 4. Because the units digit of the powers of n cycle in groups of d, where d | 4, the units digit of 4^4!+5^5!+\u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7+2023^2023! is the same as the units digit of 4^4+5^4+6^4+\u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7+2023^4. The units digit of 1^4+2^4+\u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7+9^4+10^4 is (1+6+1+6+5+6+1+6+1+0) \u2261 3 mod 10, so the units digit of 4^4 + 5^4 + 6^4 + \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 + 2023^4 is the units digit of 202 \u00b7 3, or 6. Adding back the first three terms yields a final units digit of (1 + 4 + 9 + 6) \u2261 0 mod 10.",
        "Category": "Number Sense",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Call a point P = (x, y) in the xy-plane stable if x = y. Let S denote a path from (0, 0) to (4, 4) that is solely composed of steps that increase either the x or the y-coordinate by 1. Then the expected number of stable points through which S passes can be expressed as m/n for relatively prime positive integers m and n. Compute m + n",
        "ChoiceA": "163",
        "ChoiceB": "198",
        "ChoiceC": "197",
        "ChoiceD": "291",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "163",
        "Explanation": "There are (8 4) possible paths from (0, 0) to (4, 4). By linearity of expectation, we can compute the number of paths passing through each of the stable points and divide their sum by (8 4). The number of paths passing through (i, i), for any 0 \u2264 i \u2264 4, is (2i i)(8\u22122i 4\u2212i), so the total contribution from all the stable points is (8 4) + (2 1)(6 3) + (4 2)(4 2) + (6 3)(2 1) + (8 4) = 256. Dividing this by (8 4) yields an expected value of 256/70 = 128/35, so the answer is 128 + 35 = 163.",
        "Category": "Geometry",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Let x be a complex number satisfying the equation x^4 + 2x^3 \u2212 x^2 \u2212 2x + 1 = 0. Compute the sum of all possible values of x^4 \u2212 2x^3 \u2212 x^2 + 2x \u2212 1",
        "ChoiceA": "0",
        "ChoiceB": "8",
        "ChoiceC": "12",
        "ChoiceD": "16",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "8",
        "Explanation": "Note that (x^2 + x)^2 = x^4 + 2x^3 + x^2, so (x^2 + x)^2 \u2212 2(x^2 + x) + 1 = x^4 + 2x^3 \u2212 x^2 \u2212 2x + 1. Then the given equation is equivalent to (x^2 + x \u2212 1)^2 = 0, so x^2 + x \u2212 1 = 0 and x = (\u22121\u00b1\u221a5)/2. If we let f(x) = x^4 + 2x^3 \u2212 x^2 \u2212 2x + 1 and g(x) = x^4 \u2212 2x^3 \u2212 x^2 + 2x \u2212 1, then f(\u2212x) = g(x) + 2 for all x. Therefore, we want to find the sum of all possible values of (x^2 \u2212 x \u2212 1)^2 \u2212 2. Plugging in both values of x yields a desired sum of (6 + 2\u221a5) + (6 \u2212 2\u221a5) \u2212 4 = 8.",
        "Category": "Algebra",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "A palindrome is a number that reads the same forwards and backwards, such as 11 and 121. Let S denote the set of all three-digit positive-integer palindromes that are not divisible by 11. Compute the remainder when the product of the elements of S is divided by 11",
        "ChoiceA": "9",
        "ChoiceB": "1",
        "ChoiceC": "2",
        "ChoiceD": "10",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "10",
        "Explanation": "A three-digit palindrome takes the form aba for digits 1 \u2264 a \u2264 9 and 0 \u2264 b \u2264 9. The remainder when this number is divided by 11 is (2a \u2212 b) mod 11. Observe that, for a fixed value of a, and cycling through all 10 possible values of b will yield all but one of the remainders from 0 to 10, inclusive, when divided by 11. Thus, for each value of a, the remainder when the product of the corresponding elements of S is divided by 10 is 10!/x for the missing remainder x when x is nonzero, and when x = 0, the remainder is \u22121. By Wilson\u2019s Theorem, we know that 10!/x \u2261 \u22121/x mod 11, so it suffices to find the missing remainder for each value of a. Because 10 \u2261 \u22121 mod 11, it follows that the missing remainders will be (a + a + 1) \u2261 (2a + 1) mod 11, so they are 2 + 1, 4 + 1, 6 + 1, 8 + 1, 10 + 1, 1 + 1, 3 + 1, 5 + 1, 7 + 1, which consist of every nonnegative integer from 0 to 10, inclusive, except for 1 and 10. Thus, the desired remainder is (\u22121)^9 / (10!/10\u00b71) \u2261 10 mod 11",
        "Category": "Number Sense",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "In \u25b3ABC, AB = 3, AC = 5, and the angle bisector of \u2220BAC intersects segment BC at point D. Points P and Q lie on segments AB and AC, respectively, such that DP \u22a5 AB and DQ \u22a5 AC. Given that |BD^2 \u2212 CD^2| = 6, compute PQ^2",
        "ChoiceA": "25/2",
        "ChoiceB": "25/3",
        "ChoiceC": "175/48",
        "ChoiceD": "175/24",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "25/3",
        "Explanation": "By the Angle Bisector Theorem, there exists a constant c such that BD = 3c and CD = 5c. Since |BD^2 \u2212 CD^2| = 6, c^2 = 3/8, so BC = 8c = 2\u221a6. By the Law of Cosines, we have cos(\u2220BAC) = ((2\u221a6)^2\u22123^2\u22125^2) / (\u22122\u00b73\u00b75) = 1/3, so the area of \u25b3ABC is 1/2\u00b73\u00b75\u00b72\u221a2/3 = 5\u221a2. Note that DP = DQ because the ratio of the area of \u25b3ABD to the area of \u25b3ACD is equal to the ratio of AB to AC. Therefore, (3+5)\u00b7DP/2 = 5\u221a2, so DP = DQ = 5\u221a2/4. Since m\u2220PDQ = 180 \u2212 m\u2220BAC, we have that PQ2 = 2(5\u221a2/4)^2 \u2212 2(5\u221a2/4)^2\u00b7 \u22121/3 = 25/3.",
        "Category": "Geometry",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Let a, b, and c be the distinct complex roots of x^3 \u2212 x \u2212 1 = 0. Compute (a^3 + b^2 + c)(b^3 + c^2 + a)(c^3 + a^2 + b)",
        "ChoiceA": "7",
        "ChoiceB": "3",
        "ChoiceC": "5",
        "ChoiceD": "1",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "7",
        "Explanation": "Let f(x) = x^3 \u2212 x \u2212 1. Then a^3 = a + 1, b^3 = b + 1, and c^3 = c + 1. It follows that a^3 + b^2 + c = b^2+a+c+1 = b^2\u2212b+1 since a+b+c = 0. Similarly, b^3+c^2+a = c^2\u2212c+1 and c^3+a^2+b = a^2\u2212a+1. Note that b^2 \u2212 b + 1 = (b^3+1)/(b+1) when b \u2260 \u22121, and since since b^3 \u2212 b \u2212 1 = 0, b^3 + 1 = b + 2. Thus, (a^2 \u2212 a + 1)(b^2 \u2212 b + 1)(c^2 \u2212 c + 1) = (a+2)(b+2)(c+2)/(a+1)(b+1)(c+1) = \u2212f(\u22122)/\u2212f(\u22121) = 7.",
        "Category": "Algebra",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Steven writes down two three-digit positive integers using each of the digits {1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6} exactly once. Given that the sum of the two integers is divisible by 11, find the number of unordered pairs of integers that Steven could have written",
        "ChoiceA": "24",
        "ChoiceB": "48",
        "ChoiceC": "36",
        "ChoiceD": "72",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "48",
        "Explanation": "Suppose the partition forms the two numbers abc and def. Note that both a + c \u2212 b and d + f \u2212 e cannot possibly be at least 11 because the maximum value that they can attain is 5+6\u22121 = 10. Then a + c \u2212 b + d + f \u2212 e \u2261 0 mod 11, which implies that a + c + d + f \u2261 b + e mod 11. We know that a+b+c+d+e+f = 1+2+3+4+5+6 = 21 and that 21 \u2261 10 mod 11, so 10\u2212(b+e) \u2261 (b+e) mod 11 and b + e \u2261 5 mod 11. To finish, note that {b, e} must be a permutation of either {1, 4} or {2, 3}, with no restrictions on the permutations of the other digits, so we have 2 \u00b7 2! \u00b7 4! = 96 ordered partitions, so the number of unordered pairs of three-digit integers that Steven could have written is 96/2 = 48.",
        "Category": "Combination",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Given that 1234554321/123 is an integer, compute the sum of the digits of its largest prime factor",
        "ChoiceA": "9",
        "ChoiceB": "22",
        "ChoiceC": "10",
        "ChoiceD": "16",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "10",
        "Explanation": "Note that 1234554321 = 11111\u00b7111111 and that 111111 = 1001\u00b7111 = 7\u00b711\u00b713\u00b73\u00b737. We are given that 123 | 1234554321, so 41 | 1234554321, and therefore, 41 | 11111. This yields 11111 = 41 \u00b7 271, and 271 is both prime and the desired largest prime factor, so our answer is 2 + 7 + 1 = 10.",
        "Category": "Number Sense",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Let p and q be distinct real numbers that satisfy 3\u00b7(p^3 \u2212 q^3) \u2212 2(p^2 \u2212 q^2) = p \u2212 q. Then the maximum possible value of pq is (a+b\u221ac)/d for positive integers a, b, c, and d such that c is not divisible by the square of any prime, gcd(a, d) = 1, and gcd(b, d) = 1. Compute a + b + c + d",
        "ChoiceA": "99",
        "ChoiceB": "102",
        "ChoiceC": "28",
        "ChoiceD": "115",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "115",
        "Explanation": "Let f(x) = 3x^3 \u2212 2x^2 \u2212 x = x \u00b7 (3x + 1) \u00b7 (x \u2212 1). Then the given equation is equivalent to the condition that f(p) = f(q). We can also rewrite this in the form f(x) = x(3x+1)(x\u22121). Note that p = 0 and q = 1 satisfy this condition, so the maximum possible value of pq is at least 0 \u00b7 1 = 0. Therefore, it suffices to consider the cases in which p and q have the same sign. Note that f has no roots less than \u22121/3, so if p\nand q are both negative, the maximum possible value of pq is (\u22121/3)^2 = 1/9. However, if p and q are both positive, we can divide both sides of the equation by p \u2212 q to get 3(p^2 + pq + q^2) \u2212 2(p + q) = 1 since p \u2260 q. Now let p + q = a and pq = b so that 3(a^2 \u2212 b) \u2212 2a = 1. Solving for b yields b = (3a^2\u22122a\u22121)/3, which graphs as an upwards-opening parabola. Since p and q are positive, the AM-GM inequality implies that a^2/4 \u2265 b. Conversely, any positive values of a and b satisfying this inequality corresponds to values of p and q in the form of p = (a+\u221a(a^2\u22124b))/2 and q = (a\u2212\u221a(a^2\u22124b))/2. Solving this inequality then yields a \u2208 [1/9(4 \u2212 2\u221a13), 1/9(4 + 2\u221a13)]. To maximize b, we utilize the endpoint of the interval that is farther from the vertex of the parabola, which has a-coordinate \u2212(\u22122)/(2\u00b73) = 1/3. The further endpoint is a = 1/9 \u00b7 (4 + 2\u221a13), for which we obtain b = (17+4\u221a13)/81 . This yields pq = (17+4\u221a13)/81, which is greater than 1/9, so the desried sum is 17 + 4 + 13 + 81 = 115.",
        "Category": "Algebra",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Let ABC be a triangle with AB = 49, BC = 50, and CA = 51. The angle bisector of \u2220A intersects BC at D, and points P and Q lie on AB and AC, respectively, such that DP \u2225 AC and DQ \u2225 AB. Suppose that lines PQ and BC intersect at a point R. Then the length of AR can be expressed as m/n for relatively prime positive integers m and n. Compute m + n",
        "ChoiceA": "2503",
        "ChoiceB": "2403",
        "ChoiceC": "51",
        "ChoiceD": "53",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "2503",
        "Explanation": "Note that m\u2220PAD = m\u2220BAC/2 by angle bisection, and using the given parallel lines, we also have that m\u2220PDA = m\u2220CAD = m\u2220BAC/2. Therefore, PA = PD, and similarly, we can show that QA = QD. In fact, \u25b3PAD and \u25b3QAD share a side and are congruent, so APDQ is a rhombus. By the Angle Bisector Theorem, BD has length 49/100 \u00b7 50, and since \u25b3PBD \u223c \u25b3ABC, PD = 49/100 \u00b7 51. Triangle ARD is isoscles, so AR = RD. Then \u25b3QRD \u223c \u25b3PRB, so BD = 49\u00b750/100 and BP = 49\u00b749/100. Now let BR = x. By similar triangles, BR/BP = DR/QD , so 100x/49^2 = (100x+49\u00b750) / (49\u00b751), and x = 2401/4. We want DR = BR + BD. We have that AR = DR = 2401/4 + 49/2, which is 2499/4, because BD = 49\u00b750/100, so m + n = 2499 + 4 = 2503.",
        "Category": "Geometry",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12407",
        "Question": "Compute the smallest positive integer n for which (1/((n+1)^1/3 - n^1/3) - (n(n+1))^1/3)^3 > 2024 + 3 * (n^2 * (n+1)^2)^1/3 * (((n+1)^2)^1/3 + (n^2)^1/3)",
        "ChoiceA": "16",
        "ChoiceB": "26",
        "ChoiceC": "13",
        "ChoiceD": "32",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "32",
        "Explanation": "Observe that 1/((n+1)^1/3\u2212n^1/3) = (n + 1)^2/3 + n^2/3 + n^1/3 * (n + 1)^1/3 by the difference of cubes, so left-hand side of the inequality can be rewritten as ((n + 1)^2/3 + n^2/3)^3 = (n + 1)^2 + n^2 + 3n^2/3 * (n + 1)^2/3 * ((n + 1)^2/3 + n^2/3) or 2n^2+2n+1+3n^2/3 * (n+1)^2/3 * ((n+1)^2/3+n^2/3). Since n > 0, we can cancel out the 3n^2/3 * (n+1)^2/3 * ((n+1)^2/3 + n^2/3) term on both sides of the equation, which leaves us with 2n^2 + 2n + 1 > 2024. The smallest positive integer n that satisfies this inequality is n \u2265 32.",
        "Category": "Algebra",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Compute gcd(28, 28) \u00b7 lcm(28, 28)",
        "ChoiceA": "28",
        "ChoiceB": "56",
        "ChoiceC": "784",
        "ChoiceD": "864",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "784",
        "Explanation": "Note that gcd(28, 28) and lcm(28, 28) both equal 28. The product of 28 and 28 is 784.",
        "Category": "Number Sense",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "The area of right triangle ABC is half the area of right triangle DEF. Given that AC and DF are the hypotenuses of their respective triangles and DE = 4 \u00b7 BC, compute the value of AB/EF .",
        "ChoiceA": "8",
        "ChoiceB": "1/8",
        "ChoiceC": "1/4",
        "ChoiceD": "1/2",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "Other",
        "Explanation": "The area of \u25b3ABC is 1/2\u00b7AB\u00b7BC, and the area of \u25b3DEF is 1/2\u00b7DE\u00b7EF. We are given that 2\u00b71/2\u00b7AB\u00b7BC = 1/2 \u00b7 DE \u00b7 EF, and DE = 4 \u00b7 BC, so AB \u00b7 BC = 1/2 \u00b7 4 \u00b7 BC \u00b7 EF. Finally, AB = 2 \u00b7 EF, so AB/EF = 2.",
        "Category": "Geometry",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "The 33rd term of an arithmetic sequence with common difference 3 is 3 times the 3rd term. Compute the first term of the sequence.",
        "ChoiceA": "-129",
        "ChoiceB": "39",
        "ChoiceC": "-1/3",
        "ChoiceD": "36",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "39",
        "Explanation": "Let a be the first term of the sequence so that the 3rd term is a + 2 \u00b7 3 and the 33rd term is a + 32 \u00b7 3. Then we have that 3(a + 6) = a + 96, so 3a = a + 78 and a = 39.",
        "Category": "Algebra",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Compute the number of positive integers whose digits sum to 9 and strictly decrease when read from left to right.",
        "ChoiceA": "14",
        "ChoiceB": "12",
        "ChoiceC": "16",
        "ChoiceD": "20",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "16",
        "Explanation": "For any such integer that does not end in 0, the digit 0 can be appended to create a new number still satisfying both conditions. Thus, we first count the number of such numbers with nonzero digits. The maximum number of digits is 3, since 4 + 3 + 2 + 1 > 9. For any tuple of digits, there is one way to arrange them in decreasing order. Thus, we simply compute the number of tuples with no duplicate digits that have a sum of 9. There are 3 triples: (6, 2, 1), (5, 3, 1), and (4, 3, 2). There are 4 pairs: (8, 1), (7, 2), (6, 3), and (5, 4). There is 1 singleton: (9). The number of such numbers with nonzero digits is 3 + 4 + 1 = 8. Eight more numbers can be made by appending the digit 0 to each of these, so the total count is 8 + 8 = 16.",
        "Category": "Combination",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "A textitpalindromicdate is a date with the property that the day of the month, the month number, and the year have a sum that is a palindrome. Let N be the number of calendar days strictly between the first and second palindromic dates after the year 2024. Compute the sum of the digits of N.",
        "ChoiceA": "12",
        "ChoiceB": "13",
        "ChoiceC": "19",
        "ChoiceD": "9",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "12",
        "Explanation": "The sum of the day, month, and year is greater than 2024, so the smallest possible palindromic sum is 2112. The maximum sum from the day of the month and the month number is 12 + 31 = 43, so the year must be at least 2112 \u2212 43 = 2069. The first such palindromic date is December 31, 2069. The next time the sum 2112 is achieved is in the next year, 2070, for which the sum of the day of the month and the month number is 2112\u22122070 = 42. This requires the month to be at least 11. However, November only has 30 days, so this date occurs in December. The second such palindromic date is December 30, 2070. Since 2070 is not divisible by 4, the year 2070 is not a leap year. The number of days strictly between December 31, 2069 and December 30, 2070 is 365 \u2212 2 = 363, which has a digit sum of 12.",
        "Category": "Number Sense",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Let A1A2A3A4A5A6A7A8 be a regular octagon with area M. The four segments A2A7, A3A6, A4A1, and A5A8 enclose a convex region of area N. Compute N/M.\n",
        "ChoiceA": "(3^1/2 - 1)/2",
        "ChoiceB": "(2*3^1/2 - 2)/3",
        "ChoiceC": "(2*3^1/2 - 1)/3",
        "ChoiceD": "2^1/2 - 1",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "Other",
        "Explanation": "Let s denote the side length of the octagon. By symmetry, note that the enclosed region is a square of side length s. By dividing the octagon by the lines A2A7, A3A6, A4A1, and A5A8, the area of the octagon consists of the center square with side length s, four rectangles with dimensions s by \u221as/2, and four isosceles right triangles with legs of length \u221as/2. So M = s^2 + 4 * s^2/\u221a2 + 4 \u00b7 1/2(s/\u221a2)^2 = (2 + 2\u221a2)s^2. Therefore, N/M = s^2/((2+2\u221a2)s^2) = (\u221a2 \u2212 1)/2.",
        "Category": "Geometry",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "A circle is divided into n pieces by 7 lines, all of which are either parallel or perpendicular to each of the other lines. Compute the maximum possible value of n.",
        "ChoiceA": "29",
        "ChoiceB": "20",
        "ChoiceC": "15",
        "ChoiceD": "16",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "20",
        "Explanation": "Suppose that the circle is oriented so that the cuts are either horizontal or vertical. Notice that no matter where the cuts are, x horizontal cuts will always divide the circle into x+1 strips, and y vertical cuts will divide each strip into at most y+1 pieces, for a total of (x+1)(y+1) pieces. In addition, the maximum is achieved when each horizontal cut intersects with each vertical cut in the interior of the circle, so we can place the cuts close to the circle\u2019s horizontal and vertical lines of symmetry. Since x + y = 7, the maximum value of (x + 1)(y + 1) = xy + x + y + 1 = xy + 8 is attained when xy is maximized. This happens when x and y are as close together as possible, or when (x, y) = (3, 4) or (4, 3), giving us a total of 20 pieces.\n",
        "Category": "Geometry",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Let f(x) be a polynomial of degree 3 with leading coefficient 1. Given that f(1) = 19 and f(\u22121) = 7, compute f(2) \u2212 f(\u22122).",
        "ChoiceA": "48",
        "ChoiceB": "64",
        "ChoiceC": "36",
        "ChoiceD": "32",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "36",
        "Explanation": "Let f(x) = x^3 + ax^2 + bx + c so that f(1) = 1 + a + b + c = 19 and f(\u22121) = \u22121 + a \u2212 b + c = 7. Then f(1)\u2212f(\u22121) = 12 = 2+2b, so b = 5. Observe that f(2) = 8 + 4a + 2b + c and f(\u22122) = \u22128+4a\u22122b+c so f(2) \u2212 f(\u22122) = 16 + 4b = 36.",
        "Category": "Algebra",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "A high school has a total of N students in grades 9, 10, 11, and 12. Each grade has a different number of students that is a multiple of 4. Given that each grade has at least 107 students and that the school has at most 841 students in total, compute the number of possible values of N.",
        "ChoiceA": "103",
        "ChoiceB": "98",
        "ChoiceC": "104",
        "ChoiceD": "102",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "Other",
        "Explanation": "The number of students in each grade is a multiple of 4, so N is also a multiple of 4. Since each grade has a different number of students, the minimum value of N is 108 + 112 + 116 + 120 = 4 \u00b7 114 = 456. The maximum value of N is 840, so the number of possible values of N is the number of terms in the arithmetic sequence 456, 460, 464, \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 , 840, since we can simply increase the number of students in the largest grade by increments of 4 to ensure each grade has a different number of students. The number of possible values of N is (840\u2212456)/4 + 1 = 384/4 + 1 = 97.",
        "Category": "Combination",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Let B be the circumcenter of \u25b3ACD. Given that AC = AD and AB = CD, compute AC^2/BC^2",
        "ChoiceA": "3 + (3)^1/2",
        "ChoiceB": "2 + (3)^1/2",
        "ChoiceC": "2 + 2*(3)^1/2",
        "ChoiceD": "2*(3)^1/2",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Easy",
        "Answer": "2 + (3)^1/2",
        "Explanation": "Since B is the circumcenter of \u25b3ACD, we have that BA = BC = BD = CD, so \u25b3BCD is equilateral. Let BC = CD = 2s and E be the point of intersection between line AB and segment CD so that CE = s and BE = s\u221a3. Since AE = AB + BE = 2s + s\u221a3 = s(2 +\u221a3), by the Pythagorean Theorem, we have that AC^2 = CE^2 + AE^2 = s^2 + s^2(2 + \u221a3)^2 = s^2(1 + 4 + 4\u221a3 + 3) = (8 + 4\u221a3)s^2. The desired ratio is then AC2/BC2 = (8+4\u221a3)s^2/(2s)^2 = 2 + \u221a3.",
        "Category": "Geometry",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Let N be the number of ordered triples of integers (a, b, c) such that abc = 60 and c > 1. Compute the remainder when N is divided by 9.",
        "ChoiceA": "0",
        "ChoiceB": "7",
        "ChoiceC": "8",
        "ChoiceD": "3",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "3",
        "Explanation": "Suppose a, b, and c are all positive. Since 60 has a prime factorization of 22\n\u00b7 3 \u00b7 5, there are 3 choices for which of a, b, or c is divisible by 3, 3 choices for which is divisible by 5, and 6 ways to distribute the factors of 2. There are 3\u00b73\u00b76 = 54 ways to distribute the prime factors such that a, b, and c are positive. Using complementary counting, assume c = 1, then compute the number of pairs of positive integers (a, b) with ab = 60. Since 60 has 12 divisors, there are 12 possible values of a and its corresponding value b = 60/a, so 12 of the 54 triples have c = 1. Thus, there are 54\u221212 = 42 such ordered triples such that a and b are positive and c > 1. For a given ordered triplet of positive integers, we may choose to negate exactly two of them or keep them all positive. Since c > 1, it must stay positive, so a and b are either both negative or both positive. Multiply by 2 to get a final count of 42 \u00b7 2 = 84, which when divided by 9 leaves a remainder of 3.",
        "Category": "Number Sense",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Compute the number of ordered pairs of integers (x, y) such that x^2 + y^2 < 25.",
        "ChoiceA": "81",
        "ChoiceB": "70",
        "ChoiceC": "71",
        "ChoiceD": "80",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "Other",
        "Explanation": "Since x^2 < 25, we have \u22125 < x < 5. When x is \u22124, \u22123, \u22122, \u22121, 0, 1, 2, 3, and 4, there are 5, 7, 9, 9, 9, 9, 9, 7, and 5 possible values of y, respectively. In all, we have 5 + 7 + 5 \u00b7 9 + 7 + 5 = 69 pairs.",
        "Category": "Combination",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Compute the smallest positive integer k for which \u221a(k + 0.04) is rational.",
        "ChoiceA": "25",
        "ChoiceB": "48",
        "ChoiceC": "24",
        "ChoiceD": "23",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "23",
        "Explanation": "We want \u221a(k + 1/25) = \u221a((25k+1)/25) = \u221a(25k+1)/5 to be rational, so 25k + 1 must be a perfect square. A perfect square congruent to 1 mod 25 is the square of an integer congruent to 1 or 24 modulo 25. We cannot have 25k + 1 = 1^2 because k = 0 is not allowed. So 25k + 1 \u2265 242 = 576, and thus k \u2265 23.",
        "Category": "Number Sense",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Let x and y be real numbers for which (x \u2212 i)^2 + (y \u2212 i)^2 = 1. Given that i = \u221a\u22121, compute xy.",
        "ChoiceA": "-2",
        "ChoiceB": "5/2",
        "ChoiceC": "3",
        "ChoiceD": "-3/2",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "-3/2",
        "Explanation": "Expanding, we get x^2 \u2212 2xi + y^2 \u2212 2yi = 3. Equating coefficients, we obtain x^2 + y^2 = 3 and \u22122x\u22122y = 0, or y = \u2212x. Then 2x^2 = 3, and x^2 = 3/2 = \u2212xy, so xy = \u22123/2.",
        "Category": "Algebra",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Compute the area of the region of points (x, y) in the xy-plane such that x^2 + y^2 \u2264 6x.",
        "ChoiceA": "81/4 \u03c0",
        "ChoiceB": "27/4 \u03c0",
        "ChoiceC": "81/16 \u03c0",
        "ChoiceD": "9/4 \u03c0",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "Other",
        "Explanation": "Since x^2 + y^2 \u2264 6x is an inequality that compares two continuous functions, we have that the border of the region is defined by the curve x^2 \u2212 6x + y^2 = 0. By adding 9 to both sides, we see that this is the equation of a circle, namely x^2 \u2212 6x + 9 + y^2 = 9, or (x \u2212 3)^2 + y^2 = 9. Thus, R is a circle centered at (3, 0) with radius 3, so the area is 9\u03c0.",
        "Category": "Algebra",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "In Mathopolis, dogs have either black fur or white fur. Every dog with black fur has blue eyes, and no dog with white fur has brown eyes. In addition, every dog with brown eyes has a collar, and no dog with black fur has a collar. How many of the following statements must be true?\n\u2022 Every dog has blue eyes.\n\u2022 There is at least one dog with a collar.\n\u2022 Every dog with brown eyes has black fur.\n\u2022 No dog with blue eyes has a collar.",
        "ChoiceA": "1",
        "ChoiceB": "0",
        "ChoiceC": "2",
        "ChoiceD": "4",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "1",
        "Explanation": "We consider each statement independently.\n\u2022 Every dog has blue eyes.\nSuppose we have at least one dog with white fur. Dogs with white fur do not have brown eyes, but they do not necessarily have blue eyes. This statement might be false.\n\u2022 There is at least one dog with a collar.\nSuppose we have one dog with black fur and one dog with white fur. The dog with black fur cannot have a collar. The dog with white fur cannot have brown eyes, so we cannot conclude if it has a collar or not. This statement might be false.\n\u2022 Every dog with brown eyes has black fur.\nSuppose we have a dog with brown eyes. Dogs either have white fur or black fur. This dog cannot have white fur, or else it would not have brown eyes. Thus, this dog has black fur, so every dog with brown eyes has black fur. This statement must be true.\n\u2022 No dog with blue eyes has a collar.\nSuppose we have a dog with white fur and blue eyes. This satisfies neither of the conditions for or against having a collar, so we cannot conclude whether this dog has a collar. This statement might be false.\nTherefore, only 1 of the statements is guaranteed to be true.",
        "Category": "Number Sense",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "A chicken at the origin starts a random walk. Each second, the chicken randomly chooses one of the four cardinal directions and walks one meter in that direction. The expected value of the number of meters between the chicken and the origin after three seconds can be expressed in the form (a+b*c^1/2)/d for positive integers a, b, c, and d such that b and c are prime numbers that do not divide d. Compute a + b + c + d.",
        "ChoiceA": "35",
        "ChoiceB": "15",
        "ChoiceC": "22",
        "ChoiceD": "25",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "22",
        "Explanation": "Without loss of generality, suppose the chicken starts by walking 1 meter north to (0, 1). There are 4^2 = 16 paths for the remaining two steps. On four of these paths, the chicken walks two meters in the same direction, ending at (0, \u22121), (0, 3), (2, 1), or (\u22122, 1). These points are distance 1, 3, \u221a5, and \u221a5 from the origin. On eight of the paths, the chicken walks one meter, turns left or right, and walks another meter. It ends at (0, 1), (0, \u22121), (1, 2), or (\u22121, 2), with two paths leading to each of these points, which are distance 1, 1, \u221a5, and \u221a5 from the origin. Finally, the chicken can walk one meter, turn 180 degrees, and return, ending at (0, 1), which is distance 1 from the origin. The expected distance is therefore 1/16(1(1 + 3 + \u221a5 + \u221a5) + 2(1 + 1 + \u221a5 + \u221a5) + 4(1)) = 1/16 \u00b7 (12 + 6\u221a5) = (6+3\u221a5)/8, which yields a sum of 22.",
        "Category": "Combination",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "An ice cream parlor uses ice cream cones in the shape of right circular cones with height 6 centimeters and diameter 4 centimeters. Currently, a perfectly spherical scoop of ice cream sits in the cone such that it is tangent to the cone along its rim. The parlor is considering shrinking the scoop so that the new scoop remains spherical, but its center is in the same plane as the rim of the cone. Compute the ratio of the radius of the new scoop to the radius of the current scoop.",
        "ChoiceA": "37/40",
        "ChoiceB": "4/5",
        "ChoiceC": "7/8",
        "ChoiceD": "17/20",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "Other",
        "Explanation": "Half of a cross-section of the cone is shown below, with CD and AE being the radii of the original and new scoops, respectively. We wish to compute AE/CD. We are given that AB = 6, AC = 2, CD \u22a5 BC \u22a5 AE, and BD \u22a5 AC. Thus, \u25b3ADC is similar to \u25b3ACB by a scale factor of AC/AB = 1/3. Thus, AD = 1/3 \u00b7 AC = 2/3, so CD = 2/3*\u221a10 by the Pythagorean Theorem. Similarly, AE is the altitude to the hypotenuse of \u25b3ABC. The hypotenuse of \u25b3ABC is BC = 2\u221a10. Since the area of \u25b3ABC is 1/2 \u00b7 2 \u00b7 6 = 6, we note that AE = 12/BC = 6/\u221a10 = 3/5*\u221a10. Thus, the desired ratio is (3/5 * \u221a10) / (2/3 * \u221a10) = 9/10.",
        "Category": "Geometry",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Compute the remainder when 2023^4 is divided by 16^3.",
        "ChoiceA": "113",
        "ChoiceB": "448",
        "ChoiceC": "70",
        "ChoiceD": "1505",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "1505",
        "Explanation": "Note that 16^3 = 2^12, so 2023^4 \u2261 (2^11 \u2212 25)^4 \u2261 (2^22 \u2212 2^12 \u00b7 25 + 25^2)^2 mod 16^3. Any term with a factor of 2^12 is congruent to 0, so this expression becomes (0+0+25^2)^2 \u2261 625^2 mod 16^3. To simplify further, observe that 625^2 \u2261 (2^7 \u00b7 5 \u2212 15)^2 mod 16^3 is also equivalent to 2^14 \u00b7 25 \u2212 2^8 \u00b7 5 \u00b7 15 + 225 \u2261 \u22122^8 \u00b7 16 \u00b7 5 + 2^8 \u00b7 5 + 225 mod 16^3, so the remainder when 2023^4 is divided by 16^3 is 1280+225 = 1505.",
        "Category": "Number Sense",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Compute the number of ways in which 3 dates can be picked from a set of 21 consecutive days such that no two dates are within 3 days of each other. For example, the Monday and Thursday of the same calendar week cannot both be picked, but picking Monday and Friday of the same calendar week is possible.",
        "ChoiceA": "665",
        "ChoiceB": "595",
        "ChoiceC": "365",
        "ChoiceD": "605",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Medium",
        "Answer": "Other",
        "Explanation": "There are 18 days that are not chosen. Let a be the number of days before the first chosen date, b the number of days between the first and second chosen dates, c the number of days between the second and third, and d the number of days after the third. We have a + b + c + d = 18, and b and c are at least 3. By defining x = b \u2212 3 and y = c \u2212 3, we now have a + x + y + d = 12 and a, x, y, d \u2265 0. By sticks-and-stones, the number of solutions (a, x, y, d), and therefore the number of ways to select these three dates, is (12+4\u22121  4\u22121) = 455.",
        "Category": "Combination",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Compute the sum of all integers n such that there exist complex numbers x and y satisfying x^3 = y^3 + 4 and xy = x \u2212 y = n.",
        "ChoiceA": "-3",
        "ChoiceB": "1",
        "ChoiceC": "-1",
        "ChoiceD": "4",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "-1",
        "Explanation": "Starting with 4 = x^3 \u2212 y^3, we factor the right-hand side to get 4 = (x \u2212 y)(x^2 + xy + y^2) = (x \u2212 y)((x \u2212 y)^2 + 3xy) = n(n^2 + 3n). The left hand side of the equation n(n^2 + 3n) \u2212 4 = 0 can be factored to get (n \u2212 1)(n + 2)^2 = 0, so the possible values of n are 1 and \u22122. Both work, since we can always find complex numbers with xy = x \u2212 y = n, so the desired sum is \u22121.",
        "Category": "Algebra",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Let N denote the number of values of x in the interval [0, 2024\u03c0] for which |sec x| = 1+sin x. Compute the remainder when N is divided by 9.",
        "ChoiceA": "2",
        "ChoiceB": "8",
        "ChoiceC": "6",
        "ChoiceD": "7",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "8",
        "Explanation": "Since sec x and sin x both repeat every 2\u03c0, we only need to consider the interval [0, 2\u03c0). Squaring both sides, we have 1/(cos^2(x)) = (1+sin x)^2. As 1+sin x is always positive, this is equivalent to the given equation. Let sin x = y, so we have 1/(1\u2212y)^2 = (1 + y)^2, or equivalently, 1 = (1 \u2212 y^2)(1 + y)^2 = \u2212y^4 \u2212 2y^3 + 2y + 1. Subtracting 1 from both sides yields \u2212y(y^3 + 2y^2 \u2212 2) = 0. We claim y^3 + 2y^2 \u2212 2 = 0 has exactly one real root that lies in the range (0, 1). Since this is a cubic equation, it has at least one real root. Moreover, since it is increasing for nonnegative y and 0^3 + 2 \u00b7 0^2 \u2212 2 < 0 < 1^3 + 2 \u00b7 1^2 \u2212 2, there is exactly one real root between 0 and 1. Let the real root be z. Then the values of x with the desired property in [0, 2\u03c0) are those with sin x = z, namely 0, arcsin z, \u03c0 \u2212 arcsin z, and \u03c0. There are four solutions x in an interval [0, 2\u03c0), and the interval [0, 2024\u03c0) consists of 1012 such repeated intervals. After also including the endpoint x = 2024\u03c0 as a solution, the total number of solutions x in [0, 2024\u03c0] is 1012 \u00b7 4 + 1 = 4049, which leaves a remainder of 8 when divided by 9.",
        "Category": "Algebra",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Compute the number of 6-digit positive integers such that each digit is between 1 and 6, inclusive, and the digits can be permuted in exactly 30 ways.",
        "ChoiceA": "2700",
        "ChoiceB": "1800",
        "ChoiceC": "2520",
        "ChoiceD": "2120",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "1800",
        "Explanation": "Let the number of times that each of the digits from 1 through 6 appear in a particular string be a, b, c, d, e, and f respectively, so 30 = 6!/(a!b!c!d!e!f!), since the a! permutations of the a 1s are indistinguishable, and similarly for the other digit values. That is, we have a! \u00b7 b! \u00b7 c! \u00b7 d! \u00b7 e! \u00b7 f! = 24. Since 4! = 24, none of a, b, c, d, e, and f can be more than 4, but one of them must be at least 3 for the factor of 3 to appear. If one of a, b, c, d, e, and f is 4, then exactly four of the digits match and the other two digits are unique. If one of a, b, c, d, e, and f is 3, say a, then b! \u00b7 c! \u00b7 d! \u00b7 e! \u00b7 f! = 4 = 2!2!, so two of there are two 2s. But it is impossible to have a group of 3 digits and two groups of 2 digits, because that would require at least 3 + 2 + 2 = 7 digits, while the number has only 6. So exactly 4 digits match, and we have a total of 6 \u00b7 (6  4) \u00b7 5 \u00b7 4 = 120 \u00b7 15 = 1800 strings.",
        "Category": "Combination",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Compute the number of ordered pairs (a, b) of integers a and b between 1 and 10, inclusive, that satisfy (gcd(a, b))2 \u2264 lcm(a, b).",
        "ChoiceA": "80",
        "ChoiceB": "88",
        "ChoiceC": "86",
        "ChoiceD": "85",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "85",
        "Explanation": "Because lcm(a, b) gcd(a, b) = ab, the desired inequality is equivalent to (gcd(a, b))3 \u2264 ab. We will use complementary counting, so we find the number of ordered pairs where this inequality does not hold. If a = b, the inequality does not hold when a > 1, so there are 9 such pairs. Now suppose that a > b to take advantage of the symmetry of the problem. There are no solutions violating the inequality for b = 2 or for 6 \u2264 b \u2264 10. For b = 3, b = 4, and b = 5, the only corresponding values of a violating the inequality are 6, 8, and 10, respectively. In all, there are 9 + 2 \u00b7 3 = 15 cases in which the desired inequality does not hold, so the total number of satisfactory pairs (a, b) is 100 \u2212 15 = 85.",
        "Category": "Number Sense",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Two parallel chords are drawn in a circle of radius 4 at distances of 2 and 2\u221a2 from the center of the circle. Let K denote the minimum possible area of the region bounded by the chords and the circumference of the circle. Compute the greatest integer less than or equal to 4K.",
        "ChoiceA": "23",
        "ChoiceB": "24",
        "ChoiceC": "20",
        "ChoiceD": "21",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "21",
        "Explanation": "The area is minimized when the chords are on the same side of the center. Let O be the center of the circle, and let A and B be the midpoints of the shorter and longer chords, respectively. Let CD and EF be the shorter and longer chords, respectively. The desired region is formed by removing \u25b3OEF and the segment cut off by CD from the sector with angle \u2220EOF. The segment cut off by CD is itself formed by removing \u25b3OCD from the sector with angle \u2220COD. Observe that \u2220COD = 90 and \u2220EOF = 120 by special right triangles, so the areas of the respective sectors are 90/360 \u00b7 4^2\u03c0 = 4\u03c0 and 120/360 \u00b7 4^2\u03c0 = 16/3\u03c0. Using base times height, where the chords are considered the bases, \u25b3COD has an area of 1/2 \u00b7 4 \u00b7 4 = 8 and \u25b3EOF has area 1/2 \u00b7 4\u221a3 \u00b7 2 = 4\u221a3. Then the area of the desired region is K = 16/3\u03c0 \u2212 (4\u03c0 \u2212 8) \u2212 4\u221a3 = 4/3\u03c0 + 8 \u2212 4\u221a3. Then 4K is approximately 21.04, which rounds down to 21.",
        "Category": "Geometry",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "A train traveling from Waddleton to Lemonstan at a constant speed of 20 miles per hour departs at the same time as a train traveling from Lemonstan to Waddleton at a constant speed of 25 miles per hour. Each train and each station is half a mile long, and there are 99.5 miles of track between the two stations. An ant of negligible size starts at the back of one of the trains and begins walking when the train departs. The ant walks at a constant speed directly towards the front of the train it is on such that it reaches the front of its train no later than the time at which the train reaches its destination. Compute the maximum possible number of hours between the time that the trains depart and the time at which the ant passes the front of the other train.",
        "ChoiceA": "1000/451",
        "ChoiceB": "67/30",
        "ChoiceC": "20/9",
        "ChoiceD": "1005/451",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "1000/451",
        "Explanation": "Let f(x, y) denote the number of hours it would take given that the train the ant rides on travels x miles per hour and the other train travels y miles per hour. The ant\u2019s beginning and ending points are 99.5 + 0.5 + 0.5 = 100.5 miles apart. The amount of time it takes to reach the end is equal to the amount of time its train takes to travel 100 miles, which is 100/x hours. The ant\u2019s net speed is then 100.5/(100/x) = 201/200x miles per hour, so the ant and the other train travel towards each other at a combined speed of y + 201/200x miles per hour. However, at the point in time that the ant passes the front of the other train, the combined distance traveled by the ant and the other train is only 100 miles, since the 0.5 miles at the end that the train without the ant started at will not be covered. Thus, the number of hours it will take is f(x, y) = 100/(y+201/200x) = 20000/(200y+201x). To maximize f(x, y), we minimize 200y + 201x = 200(x + y) + x, so we assign x = 20 and y = 25, for which f(20, 25) = 20000/(200\u00b725+201\u00b720) = 1000/(250+201) = 1000/451.",
        "Category": "Algebra",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Devin develops an infini-sapling, a plant whose roots enter the surface and form a fertile root bulb. Every year, fertile root bulbs can extend the roots deeper, sprouting either zero, one, or two other root bulbs. Most root bulbs sprout 1 new root bulb, but there is a miracle 1/10^9 chance of sprouting two, and an unfortunate 2/10^9 chance of sprouting none. However, regardless of how many more root bulbs it forms, a new fertile root bulb always becomes infertile after a year. Compute the expected number of total root bulbs once all root bulbs have become infertile.",
        "ChoiceA": "10^9 + 1",
        "ChoiceB": "10^18 + 1",
        "ChoiceC": "10^9",
        "ChoiceD": "10^18",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "10^9",
        "Explanation": "Each root bulb is independent of the others, so we can let r denote the total number of root bulbs that one root bulb may lead to, including itself. Let E(x) denote the expected number of root bulbs for a plant whose starting root bulb extends into x root bulbs. For example, E(0) = 1 since no further root bulbs are formed. In particular, we observe that E(1) = 1 + r and E(2) = 1 + 2r, whatever r may be. Notice that r is the weighted average of the values of E(x), so r = 2/10^9 \u00b7 E(0) + (1 \u2212 3/10^9) \u00b7 E(1) + 1/10^9 \u00b7 E(2) = (2+(10^9\u22123)(r+1)+(2r+1))/10^9. This simplifies to (2+10^9r\u22123r+10^9\u22123+2r+1)/10^9 = ((10^9\u22121)r+10^9)/10^9 = r, so r = 109.",
        "Category": "Combination",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "There exists a point P in the interior of equilateral triangle ABC such that PA = 1, PB = \u221a2, and PC = \u221a3. Then BC^2 can be expressed in the form \u221am + \u221an for positive integers m and n. Compute m + n.",
        "ChoiceA": "21",
        "ChoiceB": "11",
        "ChoiceC": "14",
        "ChoiceD": "15",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "15",
        "Explanation": "Let \u25b3CBD be the image of \u25b3ABC after a 60 rotation around B such that A maps to C, and let P\u2032 be the image of P after the rotation. Observe that BP\u2032 = \u221a2 and CP\u2032 = AP = 1. Furthermore, m\u2220PBP\u2032 = 60, so \u25b3PBP\u2032 is an equilateral triangle with side length \u221a2. By Pythagorean Theorem on \u25b3CP\u2032P, we know that \u2220CP\u2032P = 90 is right, and so \u2220BP\u2032C = 150. Using the Law of Cosines on \u25b3BP\u2032C, we have that BC^2 = 3 + \u221a6 = \u221a9 + \u221a6, so the desired sum is 15.",
        "Category": "Geometry",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Let f(k) be the exponent of the largest power of 2 dividing 9k+5. Compute f(1)+f(2)+f(3)+\u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7+f(2024).",
        "ChoiceA": "2023",
        "ChoiceB": "2024",
        "ChoiceC": "2025",
        "ChoiceD": "4048",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "2025",
        "Explanation": "Among 9 \u00b7 1 + 5, 9 \u00b7 3 + 5, 9 \u00b7 5 + 5, \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 , 9 \u00b7 2021 + 5, 9 \u00b7 2023 + 5, the even values of f(k) range from 14 to 18212, in increments of 18, which is a multiple of 2 but not of 4. Using the fact that 9 \u00b7 3+5 = 32, we have 1012 even values, 506 divisible by 4, 253 divisible by 8, 127 divisible by 16, and 64 divisible by 32. The smallest positive integer k for which f(k) is divisible by 64 is 35, so there are 32 multiples of 64, and likewise, 16 multiples of 128, 8 multiples of 256, 4 multiples of 512, 2 multiples of 1024, and 1 multiple of 2048. This gives a sum of 506\u00b71+253\u00b72+126\u00b73+63\u00b74+32\u00b75+16\u00b76+8\u00b77+4\u00b78+2\u00b79+1\u00b710+1\u00b711 = 2025.",
        "Category": "Number Sense",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    },
    {
        "ID": "12406",
        "Question": "Let S = {\u22124, \u22123, 2, 3}. Then let f(x) be a(x \u2212 p)(x \u2212 q) where a, p, and q are distinct elements of S, and let g(x) = b(x \u2212 r), where b and r are distinct elements of S. Let h(x) = f(x) \u2212 g(x). Let M denote the maximum possible achievable value of h(x) over all possible functions h(x) that have a finite global maximum. Compute \u230aM\u230b.",
        "ChoiceA": "51",
        "ChoiceB": "49",
        "ChoiceC": "50",
        "ChoiceD": "52",
        "ChoiceE": "Other",
        "Difficulty": "Hard",
        "Answer": "49",
        "Explanation": "Notice that h(x) is the difference between a quadratic polynomial and a linear polynomial, so h(x) is itself a quadratic. Observe that h(x) = a(x\u2212p)(x\u2212q)\u2212b(x\u2212r) = ax^2\u2212(ap+aq+b)x+(apq+br). Since h(x) has a finite global maximum, h(x) must have a negative leading coefficient, so a must be negative. Furthermore, this is a quadratic whose vertex lies on x = \u2212(\u2212ap\u2212aq\u2212b)/2a = 1/2 \u00b7 (p + q + b/a). Plugging this in yields that the maximum value of h is h(1/2(p + q + b/a)) = a(1/2(b/a + q \u2212 p)) * (1/2(b/a + p \u2212 q)) \u2212 b(1/2(p + q + b/a) \u2212 r) = a/4(ba + q \u2212 p)(b/a + p \u2212 q) \u2212 b/2(p + q + b/a \u2212 2r). This simplifies as a/4(b^2/a^2 \u2212 (p \u2212 q)^2) \u2212 b/2(p + q + b/a \u2212 2r) = \u2212b^2/4a \u2212 a/4(p \u2212 q)^2 \u2212 b/2(p + q) + br. We ought to pick an r that is the same sign as b, since we can always do so and that will in\u0002crease the sum. Recall that a, p, and q are all distinct, and b \u2260 r. We proceed to take cases on p + q. If p + q is nonnegative, then b should be negative and equal to \u22124 because (\u22124)(\u22123) > (3)(2) and we want to maximize b^2/(4(\u2212a)) + (\u2212b)/2(p + q). Otherwise, we see that p + q \u2265 2 \u2212 4 = \u22122 because a is negative, and b^2/(4(\u2212a)) \u2212 (p + q) \u00b7 b/2 + br \u2264 9/(4(\u2212a)) + 3 + 6 when b is positive. By taking b = \u22123 and r = \u22124, we can achieve 9/(4(\u2212a)) \u2212 (p + q) \u00b7 b/2 + br \u2265 9/(4(\u2212a)) \u2212 3 + 12 with negative b. We are now trying to maximize \u2212b^2/4a \u2212 a/4(p \u2212 q)^2 \u2212 b/2(p + q) + 12. Without loss of generality, suppose p > q. Then p should be 3 since this only increases the sum. We claim q should be negative: if it is not, then q = 2, so the relevant part of the sum is (\u2212a)/4 \u00b7 1 + (\u2212b)/2(5), and we can improve on this by taking q to be the one of \u22124 and \u22123 that is not a. Doing this yields (\u2212a)/4 \u00b7 (3 \u2212 q)^2 + (\u2212b)/2(3 + q) = (\u2212a)/4 \u00b7 1 + (\u2212b)/2(5) + (\u2212a)/4 \u00b7 [(3 \u2212 q)^2 \u2212 1] + (\u2212b)/2(q \u2212 2), so the desired result holds because (\u2212a)/4 \u00b7 [(3 \u2212 q)^2 \u2212 1] + (\u2212b)/2(q \u2212 2) \u2265 3/4 \u00b7 [6^2 \u2212 1] + 4/2(\u22126) = 3/4 \u00b7 35 \u2212 12 > 0. Now note that choosing b = \u22124 is optimal because 16/(4(\u2212a)) + 4/2(p + q) > 9/(4(\u2212a)) + 3/2(p + q), which is true since (p, q) = (3, \u22123) when a = \u22124 and (p, q) = (3, \u22124) when a = \u22123, with the inequality holding in both cases. Finally, we must choose between (a, p, q, b, r) = (\u22124, 3, \u22123, \u22124, \u22123) and (a, p, q, b, r) = (\u22123, 3, \u22124, \u22124, \u22123), which yield maxima of 49 and 583/12 < 49, respectively, so the desired maximum is M = 49.",
        "Category": "Algebra",
        "Type": "Sprint"
    }
]